# Dr. Micheline Campbell

Research Associate, UNSW Sydney

## Professional summary

I have a PhD in speleothem palaeoclimatology and am currently employed as a research associate at the University of New South Wales, contributing to the Australian Research Council Discovery Project "Reconstructing Australia's fire history from cave stalagmites". My PhD research focused on stalagmite-based climate proxy records and associated karst geomorphology and groundwater hydrology, and I also have experience in the surface hydrology and palaeoclimate-water security nexus.

#### Education

- Aug 2014 PhD (Geography), School of Agriculture and Environment, The University Jul 2019 of Western Australia, Perth, Western Australia, Australia.
- Jul 2013 BA (Hons, 1st Class) (Geography), School of Geography, Planning, and
  Jun 2014 Environmental Management, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD,
  Australia.
- Feb 2010 **BA (Geography and Spanish)**, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Dec 2012 QLD, Australia.

### Experience

#### Research

- Jun 2021 **Research Associate**, School of Biological, Earth and Environmental Sciences, present University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia.
  - Contributing to the ARC Discovery Project "Reconstructing Australia's fire history from cave stalagmites"
- Jul 2020 **Postdoctoral Researcher**, School of Geography, University College Dublin, Jun 2021 Dublin/Brisbane, QLD, Ireland/Australia.
  - O Contributed to the project 'Using Palaeo-climate Proxies for Water Security Planning'
  - Undertook the majority of data science tasks for the development of a new database of Australian climate proxy data
- Feb 2020 **Scientist**, Land and Water Science Unit, QLD Dept. of Natural Resources, Jul 2020 Mining and Energy, Rockhampton, QLD, Australia.

- Aug 2019 **Research Assistant**, School of Agriculture and Environment, University of Dec 2019 Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- Aug 2014 PhD Researcher, School of Agriculture and Environment, University of Jul 2019 Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.

#### Teaching

- 2018 **Tutor: Geographies of a Global City**, School of Agriculture and Environment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- 2018 Course Co-Coordinator and Lecturer: Catchment and River Processes, School of Agriculture and Environment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.
- 2014–2018 Tutor: Catchment and River Processes, School of Agriculture and Enviroment, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia.

Teaching contributions include the delivery and creation of content for undergraduate and masters level units, both in the classroom/laboratory and in the field. Catchment and River Processes, which I taught into for my entire time at UWA, consistently achieved high student ratings.

## — Funding and scholarships

- 2023 ANSTO 24 hours of beamtime on the XFM line at the Australian Synchrotron (experiment 19157).
  - 0 \$32 784
- 2022 ANSTO 48 hours of beamtime on the XFM line at the Australian Synchrotron (experiment 17897).
  - 0 \$65 568
- 2022 ANSTO 144 hours of beamtime on the IRM line at the Australian Synchrotron (experiment 17905).
  - 0 \$196 704
- 2022 ANSTO 48 hours of beamtime on the IRM line at the Australian Synchrotron (experiment 18777).
  - o \$65 568
- 2021 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Early Career Researcher Grant.
  - o \$10 000
- 2021 University of New South Wales UNSW Science Covid-19 Strategic Support Grant.
  - o \$4 000
- 2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Travel grant.  $_{\odot}$  \$1~000

- $2017\,$  Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group Travel grant.
- 2016 University of Western Australia Travel grant.
  - 0 \$1 850
- 2015–2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Postgraduate Ressarch Award Stipend.
  - o \$7 500pa
- 2015–2018 Australian Institute of Nuclear Science and Engineering Postgraduate Research Award Analytical Budget.
  - o \$10 000pa
- $2014\hbox{--}2018 \quad \textbf{Australian Government Research Training Program Stipend}.$ 
  - o \$26 000pa
- 2014–2015 Snowy Hydro Ltd. Stipend.
  - o \$5 000pa
  - 2014 University of Western Australia Stipend.
    - o \$3 000

#### Publications

- Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Treble, P. C., Baker, A., Kosarac, N., Coleborn, K., Wynn, P. M., & Schmitt, A. K. (2023). A Review of Speleothems as Archives for Paleofire Proxies, With Australian Case Studies. *Reviews of Geophysics*, 61(2), e2022RG000790. https://doi.org/10.1029/2022RG000790
- 2. Cahill, N., Croke, J., Campbell, M., Hughes, K., Vitkovsky, J., Kilgallen, J. E., & Parnell, A. (2023). A Bayesian time series model for reconstructing hydroclimate from multiple proxies. *Environmetrics*, n/a(n/a), e2786. https://doi.org/10.1002/env.2786
- 3. Croke, J., Vítkovský, J., Hughes, K., Campbell, M., Amirnezhad-Mozhdehi, S., Parnell, A., Cahill, N., & Dalla Pozza, R. (2021). A palaeoclimate proxy database for water security planning in Queensland Australia. *Scientific Data*, 8(1), 292. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-021-01074-8
- 4. McGowan, H., Campbell, M., Callow, J. N., Lowry, A., & Wong, H. (2020). Evidence of wet-dry cycles and mega-droughts in the Eemian climate of southeast Australia. Scientific Reports, 10(1), 1–10. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-75071-z
- 5. McGowan, H., Callow, J. N., Soderholm, J., McGrath, G., Campbell, M., & Zhao, J. (2018). Global warming in the context of 2000 years of Australian alpine temperature and snow cover. *Scientific Reports*, 8(1), 4394. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-22766-z
- 6. Campbell, M., Callow, J., McGrath, G., & McGowan, H. (2018). Co-authorship analysis of the speleothem proxy-climate community: working together to tackle the big problems. *International Journal of Speleology*, 47(2), 165–172. https://doi.org/10.5038/1827-806X.47.2.2159
- 7. Campbell, M., Callow, J. N., McGrath, G., & McGowan, H. (2017). A multimethod approach to inform epikarst drip discharge modelling: Implications for palaeo-climate reconstruction. *Hydrological Processes*, 31(26), 4734–4747. https://doi.org/10.1002/hyp.11392

## Media and reports

- 1. Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Treble, P. C., & Baker, A. (2023). Using Cave Formations to Investigate Ancient Wildfires. *Eos*, 104. http://eos.org/editors-vox/using-cave-formations-to-investigate-ancient-wildfires
- 2. Campbell, M., & Barrows, T. (2023). Continuing the conversation on equity, diversity, and inclusion in AQUA. In *Quaternary Australasia* (Vol. 40).

## Conference presentations (presenting only)

#### Talks

- Dec 2022 Towards the development of fire proxies in speleothems using geochemical signatures in ashes from bushfires, 2022 AQUA Biennial, Adelaide, Australia, Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Naeher, S., Treble, P., Grierson, P., Sinclair, D., Howard, D., Baker, A..
- Feb 2022 Reconstructing Australia's fire history from cave stalagmites, 13th International Conference on Southern Hemisphere Meteorology and Oceanography, New Zealand (online), Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Kosarac, N., Treble, P., Baker, A.
- Nov 2021 Applying an open access palaeoclimate database for Australia, climate reconstructions, and water security planning in Queensland, Seminar Panel, Australia, Croke, J., Vitkovsky, J., Hughes, K., Campbell, M., Dalla Pozza, R.
- Feb 2017 A geophysical approach to inform epikarst drip discharge modelling: Implications for palaeo-climate reconstruction, Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group 17th Biennial Conference, Greytown, New Zealand, Campbell, M., Callow, J.N., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A.

#### Posters

- Apr 2023 **Speleothems as archives for palaeofire proxies**, EGU General Assembly, Vienna, Austria, Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Treble, P.C., Baker, A., Kosarac, N., Coleborn, K., Wynn, P., Schmitt, A.K..
- Dec 2022 Stalagmites as high-resolution archives of past fire severity, Synchrotron User Meeting, Melbourne, Australia, Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Treble, P., Baker, A., Howard, D., Hankin, S.
- Jul 2022 Stalagmites as high-resolution archives of past fire severity, Climate Change, The Karst Record IX, Innsbruck, Austria, Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Treble, P., Baker, A., Howard, D., Hankin, S.

- Dec 2021 Speleothems as palaeofire archives a synthesis and meta-analysis of data and methods, American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting, New Orleans, USA (online), Campbell, M., Treble, P., McDonough, L., Baker, A., Kosarac, N.
- Nov 2021 Speleothem 14C is unlikely to be impacted by wildfire case studies from Western Australia and Tasmania, Accelerator Mass Spectroscopy 15th International Conference, Sydney, Australia, Campbell, M., McDonough, L., Kosarac, N., Treble, P., Markowska, M., Baker, A., Hua, Q.
- Apr 2018 Climate patterns in South-east Australia: the Last Interglacial vs. the last 2K, EGU General Assembly, Vienna, Austria, Campbell, M., Callow, J.N., McGowan, H.A., McGrath, G.S., Wong, H.
- Feb 2017 First Insights of the Eemian Hydroclimate of the Snowy Mountains, Australia, Australian and New Zealand Geomorphological Group 17th Biennial Conference, Greytown, New Zealand, Campbell, M., Wong, H., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A., Callow, J.N.
- Dec 2016 First Insights of the Eemian Hydroclimate of the Snowy Mountains, Australia, American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting, San Francisco, USA, Campbell, M. Wong, H., McGrath, G.S., McGowan, H.A., Callow, J.N.

#### Service

- Jul 2023 Session Convenor, INQUA Roma 2023.
- Jul 2023  $\odot$  Co-Convenor for the session "Session 118: Cave deposits for in deep understanding Quaternary climate and environment"
- Apr 2023 Session Convenor, EGU General Assembly 2023.
- Apr 2023  $\, \circ \,$  Co-Convenor and co-chair for session "Fire in the Earth system: understanding effects across spatiotemporal scales"
- Nov 2022 UOW Honours thesis examiner.
- Nov 2022
- Jul 2022 Session Co-Chair, Climate Change the Karst Record IX.
  - Jul 2022 Co-Chair for session 'Cave Monitoring'
- Aug 2021 Executive Committee Member, Australasian Quaternary Association.
  - Present O IT and communications officer
    - Organising committee for AQUA's mentorship program in 2022 and 2023
- Aug 2017 Participant, Science in Schools Program.
- Aug 2017 Travelled to a regional town to share some love for science with primary school kids
- Jan 2016 Co-Convenor, SEE LearnR Workshop.
- Mar 2016 Organised a short series of 'Introduction to R' courses for the students and staff of the School of Earth and Environment
  - O Presented 'Introduction to ggplot2'
  - O Presented 'Introduction to R'

- Feb 2015 Postgraduate representative to the School of Earth and Environment.
  - Jul 2017 Led the organisation of 2 annual symposia for postgraduate students within the school.
    - O Reported student concerns to the School administration
    - O Support and troubleshooting for new students
- Oct 2014 Guest presenter, ENVT2221: Global Climate Change and Oct 2014 Biodiversity.
  - O Presented 'Palaeo-climate and Stalagmites' for 2nd-year Biology students at UWA

## Completed peer reviews

- 2023 Climate of the Past.
- 2023 Nature Communications.
- 2023 Geochimica et cosmochimica acta.
- 2022 Paleoceanography and Paleoclimatology.
- 2021 Geology.

## Professional development

- 2022 Science Meets Parliament. Online
- 2020 Advanced R Workshop. The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2020 Intermediate R Workshop. The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2018 Weathering Climate Change: How have humans coped with climate change-and how will we continue to do so. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2018 Masterclass in Creating Opportunities and Developing your Research Skills. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2016 Synthesis II From dynamics of structure to function of complex networks. TU Dresden, Germany
- 2016 Water on Earth: origin, reservoirs, and its global cycle. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2016 Fundamentals of the analysis of networks. The University of Western Australia, Australia
- 2014 Writing and publishing in scientific journals. The University of Western Australia, Australia

## Professional memberships

Aug 2021 - European Geosciences Union.

Present

Jul 2021 - Australasian Quaternary Association.

Present

Jul 2021 - American Geophysical Union.

Present